All right, here's where I tell you that
youth culture in the 1960s went
positively crazy what with all the
liberalism and the long hair and the
relations of the intimate nature. And
you, my dear pupil, have been invited to
that counterculture party. So, if you're
ready to get them brain cows milked,
let's get to it. Okay, so the baby boom
generation came of age in the 1960s and
were thus influenced not by the
sacrifice and patriotism of the Great
Depression and World War II, but rather
by the frothing cauldron of cultural
change that occurred during the Civil
Rights Movement. And as a result, the
actions of young people were a profound
catalyst for change in the 1960s. And
the first big change you need to know is
that some youth organizations pushed for
even greater liberal reforms. Greater
than what, says you? Well, says I,
remember what I said a few videos ago,
namely that the rollout of Lyndon B.
Johnson's sweeping policies in the Great
Society, which built on the foundation
laid by the New Deal, marked the high
point of modern liberalism in American
history. In other words, if you were
alive in the 1960s and you were a
liberal, then as we say here in the
South, you were happier than a bird with
a french fry. But as it turned out, only
the older liberal birds were happy about
the french fry, while the younger
liberal birds were like, "You look so
stupid with that french fry." Or to say
it plain, during the 1960s, a growing
movement of young Americans rejected the
old liberalism of the New Deal and Great
Society era. And this rejection included
but was certainly not limited to a sharp
criticism of federal activism from the
federal government and civil rights
legislation, anti-poverty programs, and
the various Cold War interventions
inspired by the containment policy. If
you're following along closely, you
might be tempted to think that what I'm
talking about here is a new generation
of conservative youth who despise
liberalism and wanted to kick it to the
curb as is the custom of conservatives.
But no, these young people didn't reject
the major tenets of liberalism because
they were conservative, but because they
felt that the old liberalism had not
been liberal enough. In fact, they had
come to believe that the old liberalism
was too cautious and too bureaucratic to
actually make any meaningful progress in
the pursuit of correcting social
injustices. And so, in 1961, Tom Hayden,
a college student who had learned the
ropes of grassroots activism from his
participation in voter registration
drive sponsored by the Student
Nonviolent Coordinating Committee,
created what he called the New Left. And
so, to that and Hayden played a
significant role in the growth and
influence of the banner organization for
the New Left, namely the Students for a
Democratic Society. In 1962, the SDS
published its Port Huron Statement,
which outlined the beliefs of this new
movement, which included a condemnation
of the immorality of Cold War foreign
policy, as well as the
military-industrial complex.
Additionally, the statement called for a
return of political power to the people
by advocating for policies that
facilitated a more participatory
democracy. Furthermore, the statement
took aim at the growth and seemingly
unlimited power of the executive branch
and conducted military policy throughout
And then it also called for more drastic
efforts to eliminate the social systems
that created poverty and racism. On this
count, advocates of the New Left pointed
out that while the old left guard
cheered the passage of civil rights
legislation, there was a big difference
between legal freedom and real freedom
for minorities. In other words, while
the Civil Rights Act and the Voting
Rights Act eliminated racial
discrimination on paper, segregation
still existed and urban poverty remained
largely untouched. And so, the New Left
pushed for policies that would not only
address surface racism, but also work to
solve the problems of systemic racism
that laws and policies, by their very
nature, could not reach. And then the
real moment for the growth and national
emergence of the New Left came during
the Vietnam War. And that is a saucy
tale, which I shall tell presently. But
first, let me mention that if you want
to get a five on that APUSH national
exam, then you might want to check out
my Heimler review guide, which has
everything you need to study as fast as
possible, not to mention a healthy dose
of sax. And you may procure it, if you
so desire, at the link in the
description. Okay, so the cauldron of
the New Left is starting to bubble and
here comes the Vietnam War to get that
thing steaming like a boss. Yes, the New
Left grew in membership and influence at
the very same moment that the US was
escalating its war in Vietnam. And it
was the New Left's perception of the
deep and abiding immorality of this war
that radicalized many members of this
movement and led to widespread anti-war
protest. And I'm going to tell you about
three of them. First was the arrest and
conviction of the heavyweight champion
boxer Muhammad Ali. So, in 1967, Ali
refused to submit to the Vietnam
military draft when his number was
called. And that's because, he
explained, as a Muslim, his conscience
would not allow him to fight in a war
not commanded by Allah. And so, Ali,
like many other draftees, sought an
exemption from the war as a
conscientious objector. But if you
recall from the video on the Vietnam
War, President Lyndon Johnson was facing
the increasing pressure of the
unpopularity of this war and a growing
resistance to the draft. And so, when
someone as popular and well-known as
Muhammad Ali was making headlines as a
conscientious objector, well, I you
know, Johnson got real grumpy. Anyway,
in the end, Ali was sentenced to five
years in prison and made to pay a
$10,000 fine, not to mention he was
stripped of his boxing title. And to be
clear, this sentence was about as
extreme and harsh a penalty a person
could receive for refusing to comply
with the draft. But the court who tried
it wanted to make an example out of Ali
and therefore quell any other anti-war
sentiment that his arrest might inspire.
But here's where I tell you Ali's arrest
had the exact opposite effect. Instead
of calming anti-war sentiment, it
actually set it on fire and that fire
soon spread to inspire other anti-war
protest. And that leads us to the second
example of youth anti-war protest, and
that was the 1967 March on the Pentagon.
So, just four months after Ali's arrest,
the SDS, in conjunction with several
other groups, organized a massive
anti-war demonstration held in front of
the Pentagon. there, demonstrators
publicly denounced President Johnson's
escalation of the war because it always
seemed that the president promised that
just a little more pressure and a few
more troops would bring the war to a
close. But that never seemed to be true
and it never seemed to be enough.
Additionally, the president also
reassured the American people that the
US was on the verge of victory, but that
narrative was starkly contradicted by
constant television reports from
journalists on the ground in Vietnam.
And so, these perceived lies provided
enormous amounts of kindling for the
fires of their protest. Additionally,
the demonstrators also protested the
injustice of the draft. because draft
laws could forcibly conscript
18-year-olds to fight in the war while
the voting age in most states was 21.
Therefore, protesters highlighted the
injustice of being forced to fight an
immoral war while having no political
agency to change the policy. Anyway, the
March on the Pentagon marked a turning
point in youth-led activism in the 1960s
and brought the anti-war movement into
national focus. Like, no longer was
anti-war sentiment decentralized and on
the fringe. It was now represented in
mass and centralized groups of organized
protest. Additionally, it demonstrated
to those in the halls of power that the
New Left could not be ignored. Now, in
terms of policy, the March didn't
actually change that much in the short
term, but four years later states
ratified the 26th Amendment, which
lowered the voting age from 21 to 18.
And then third, probably the most
notorious example of youth-led anti-war
protest occurred in 1970 at Kent State
University. So, here several thousand
students gathered to protest Richard
Nixon's announcement that he was
widening the scope of the Vietnam War by
initiating a series of bombing raids on
Cambodia, which was ironic since he
campaigned on promises to de-escalate
the war. Now, the gathering began as a
peaceful protest, but soon the Ohio
National Guard showed up and ordered the
crowd to disperse. When the students did
not leave, the guardsmen fired tear gas
into the gathering and some students
responded by hurling rocks back at the
soldiers. Long story short, things
escalated very quickly and in the midst
of confusing signals and orders, the
National Guard opened fire on the
protesters, killing four students and
wounding nine others. As a result, the
members of the New Left were even more
radicalized after the federal government
had used deadly force to silence their
protest against what they considered an
immoral war. And then in the wider
population, public opinion on the war
became even more sharply divided and
people's trust in their own government
sank to a new low. Okay, and finally,
let's talk about everyone's favorite
youth phenomenon during the 1960s and
that's the counterculture. So, while the
New Left was a more formal manifestation
of youth activism in the 1960s, far
greater numbers of young people were
drawn to a more generalized rejection of
cultural norms that they inherited from
their parents. So, counterculture youth
cast off the restraints of societal
conformity and overturned cultural norms
by means of experimental drug use,
rebellious styles of clothing, changes
in sexual norms, and embracing new
tastes in music. Now, the most iconic
image of this movement was the hippie,
who dressed in ways completely foreign
to traditional American culture. And the
most visible manifestation of the hippie
movement was in San Francisco's
Haight-Ashbury district, where hippies
gathered into a kind of communal living
based on countercultural ideals and drug
use and the music of the era. And
together, they ingested prodigious
amounts of marijuana and psychedelic
drugs like LSD, which they considered
fundamental to the hippie mindset and
created the occasion for the unification
of the community. Additionally,
counterculture youth rejected the sexual
norms of their parents and embraced what
they called free love. obviously, this
commitment was a patent critique on the
sexual norms of their parents'
generation. Additionally, the hippie
movement prized informality. Like, not
only did their clothes and general
appearance critique the prim and proper
styles of the 1950s, they also valued
informality in their music. For example,
their parents liked to listen to the
fine-tuned, well-trained voices of the
crooners like Frank Sinatra. But in
stark contrast to that, a key figure of
the counterculture music scene was Bob
Dylan, who indeed wrote lyrics like a
poet, but whose singing sounded like a
lawnmower with a bad case of post-nasal
drip. no judgment from this guy. Like, I
love Bob Dylan. He's just using what the
good lord gave him and I am all together
here for it. Anyway, one of the crowning
achievements of the counterculture
movement was the Woodstock Music
Festival held in 1969, in which almost
400,000 people were in attendance. They
were free, some were naked, many were
high as a kite, and for several days
they listened to music from folks like
Jimi Hendrix and Crosby, Stills, Nash
and Young, and Joan Baez, who gave voice
to their cultural rebellion. But the
truth is, the body and mind can only go
on for so long being assaulted with
powerful psychedelic drugs. And so, by
the 1970s, the counterculture had kind
of fizzled out because of those
excesses. All right, you can click here
to watch all my other Unit 8 videos, or
you can click here to grab my APUSH
Heimler review guide, which has
everything you need to help you get a
five on that national exam. I'm glad you
came around and I'll catch on the
flip-flop. Heimler out.